[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net. SE radio is brought to you
by the ITE computer society and by it
software magazine online at
[Music]
computer.org/software. Fly machines from
fly.io are fast launching hardware
isolated virtual machines that spin up
in milliseconds. They're the perfect
place to deploy even the sketchiest user
or LLM generated code. If something
breaks, just spin up a fresh machine and
you're good to go. Plus, Fly Machines
scale to zero when they're not needed,
so you only pay for what you use.
Fly.io. Built by humans, loved by
[Music]
robots. Welcome to Software Engineering
Radio. I'm your host, Gregory Caphammer.
Today's guest is Will McGugan. He's the
creator of Rich and Textual and the CEO
and founder of Texturalize. Will,
welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you, guys. It's good to be here.
Hey, I'm glad that you could be on the
podcast today. We're going to be talking
about textbased user interfaces and
command line user interfaces, sometimes
called TUI and CLIs. Are you ready to
dive into the conversation? Very much
so. Yes. All right. So, you're well
known for creating rich and textual,
which are two libraries for building
CLIs and Tuys in the Python programming
language. And before we get started and
go into those details, perhaps you could
start by telling us a little bit more
what is a CLI and what is a 2E and how
are they similar to and different from
each other? Sure. So, CLI, command line
interface, is essentially what you use
when you're in terminal for the most
part. You type a command might have some
options and switches hit return and you
get a response and that's basically
command line interface. So that command
is an interface to program software to E
stands for text or user interface and
it's basically a user interface. So
there's buttons and text and scroll bars
etc. Um but the interface is composed of
text and it lives inside your terminal.
So when you run a command it pops up
this user interface in your terminal.
You can interact with it in much the
same way as as a desktop application or
a web application. You can work in there
and then when you're done, hit control Q
and then you're back to the command
line. It's like a a user interface that
stays inside the terminal when you need
it. Okay, that's helpful. Now, there's
many ways that as engineers we can build
and ship applications and use
applications. So, we could also have a
web- based application or a graphical
user interface. From your perspective,
what are the benefits of using a 2E or a
CLI, especially if you're a developer?
They tend to be very responsive and very
quick and very snappy and there's less
context switching. I mean, I I used to
be a web developer. I kind of use the
web a lot like most people do, but
there's quite a lot of context switching
when you go between web application,
browser tab, etc. But the benefits of 2
running in the terminal is like it stays
in your own flow. So, it's like
everything is in one place and it's
snappy and responsive and it comes up
when you need it. It's very quick to
interact with and it goes away as
quickly when you don't need it. Okay,
we're going to use rich and textual as
like a vehicle for exploring 2 and CLIs
in greater detail. So, to get started
with this next phase of our
conversation, can you tell us a little
bit about what rich is and what textual
is? So rich, this library I wrote a
number of years ago now and its purpose
is basically to write better formatted
content to the terminal. People have
been using terminals for multiple
decades and we've grown quite accustomed
to the output. It tends to be
monochrome, tends to be unforatted, so
you won't even have text wrapping. It'll
just be kind of split into the next line
and the output can often be quite
difficult to visually parse. Rich
basically writes easier to visually
parse information. So it can format it.
It can add color and style and it can
change the layout. So you're basically
seeing the same data, but it's just much
easier to read at a glance and it gives
developers the tools to basically write
CLIs which are much more friendly to
most developers. So, you mentioned words
like friendly and easy to use, and I've
actually either built or used a number
of different apps that are written with
rich and textual. Can you give us a
couple concrete examples and explain why
they're friendly and easy to use? Sure.
So, Rich has a number of different I
call them renderables. In retrospect,
it's a poor name, but basically, it's
just one method of transforming some raw
data into some visual output. So, you
can write a table, for instance. Tables
are remarkably tricky to do. If you ever
try to write a table before rich, you'll
find it's very difficult to format all
the content, especially when the cells
the data in the table can change size.
You know, if it's too large, you might
have to wrap it and then you have to
pick the optimum number of rows to fit
inside the terminal. But rich does all
that. So if you got tabular data, you
can write it with rich and then you can
easily review it in the terminal. And
most of the renderables are like that.
They just take data that you've
calculated in your app and they present
it to the user in a much easier to read
way. The example with tables and rich is
a good one. Can you give an example when
it comes to using textual? What kinds of
applications or features would we find
in a textual application?
Yeah. So textual adds essentially a
layer over rich. Textual uses rich under
the hood and it can build interactive
apps. So often in the command line you
write a command you might wait a little
bit and then you'll get response there
but with textual it's an application
much like a website or desktop
application and it's something you can
interact with write data click buttons
and do your work there. And then these
apps can be pretty much anything really.
It's quite often used for developer
related tools. Things like interacting
with databases, forms, APIs, that kind
of thing. It's for work which is a bit
more detailed than your average CLI cuz
a CLI you just get the data out. There
it is. You look at it. But a textual
app, you want to interact with it. You
want to do little things. You want to
remove things, add, move things. So CRUD
type operations and then see it
immediately. and then various layers of
functionality on top of that. So yeah,
it's basically applications running
inside the terminal. Can you give a
specific example of maybe one of your
favorite applications that has been
built with textual? What would it look
like on the screen and how would someone
actually interact with it? Sure. So we
got Harlequin.sh. This has been around
for a while. It's one of the most
popular textual tools at the time
certainly. And basically it's an
interface to databases. So you connect
to a database could be MySQL, posgress
or even SQL light and you see a tree
view of all your tables which you can
navigate with the keys or the mouse. You
can click on them and you can also enter
SQL into like a dialogue box. It's
nicely formatted and syntax highlighted.
You enter the SQL, you run the query,
and then you see results in a table, and
you can navigate that table again with
the mouse or the cursor keys to explore
the results of your query. And that's
become really popular actually because
previously if you want to do that inside
terminal, yes, you can do of course you
can edit a SQL command and run it. The
data that comes out is probably not
particularly well formatted. So you
might have to take the data and do
something else to visualize it. But with
Harley Quinn, everything's in that one
window and it's easy to use and it's
very easy to explore. One of the
advantages I think of textual app over
CLI is you can go straight into the
textual app and explore it with the
mouse and the keys. You can go from
knowing nothing about it to being
moderately proficient in tens of
minutes. Yeah, I really like that one. I
think Harley Quinn's a very good
example. An app which doesn't have to be
in the terminal. This could be a desktop
app, could be a web app, but the virtue
of it being that terminal means that
it's right where you want it. Yeah. You
mentioned the idea of exploration, and I
think that's a good one. I often find
that Tuies are nice from the perspective
of discoverability because I can see
various things on my screen, and if
there's a tree view, I can click on
parts of the tree view and expand them
or contract them. And I think you're
right, exploration and discoverability
are really important. Now when I think
of discoverability I read something
really interesting which is that textual
is a 2y framework but that somehow it
can also ship it to the web. Can you
explain that a little bit further? So we
have a couple of technologies which
basically does just that. The textual
app running in the terminal is a default
setting but you can serve it to the web.
So if you run the textual serve command
which comes built in it'll create a link
uh you click on that link and then you
can interact with the same app and it
looks much the same almost identical
actually to the app running in the
terminal but because it's in the web
browser you can share on your network.
You could also share on the public
internet if you wanted to and the
advantage of that is basically that
known developers can find it more
accessible. Textual apps are easy to
use, but not everyone is familiar with a
terminal. Terminals are on every desktop
computer ever shipped. Um, but it's
pretty much only developers and
technical people that know about it.
Others might struggle with it, but when
it's in the web, you can share that link
and anyone can use it. And the textual
apps are built such that you don't need
to be technical to use it. Once it's on
your screen, you might think it has a
kind of a retro aesthetic because it's
built up from a matrix of characters,
but apart from that, everything's there
that you'd expect from any application.
You just click things and the click
responds to your input on the screen. So
yeah, so we have textual serve which
runs a web application locally. We've
got textual web which creates the
application and runs it on the public
internet. So you don't have to worry
about firewalls and serving things etc.
The application is just there. You write
it locally. You run it with texture web
and then you've got a public link which
you can share with people on your team
or anyone else. So that sounds
incredible. When I use textual web, my
thing is then publicly available on the
internet. Do I have to provision a
server or create a digital ocean
droplet? How does that actually work?
You would basically the app runs on the
same machine where you've installed
texture web. It connects to our server
via websockets and then the public
viewer of that link connects to our
websocket server. So when they connect
to the URL, it opens up an instance of
the application on your server. This
could be your laptop or your digital
ocean drop etc. And whilst that browser
tab is open, the user can interact with
the application that's running on your
server or servers. So we'll investigate
that in greater detail when we talk
later a little bit more about how you
built those features. But I wanted to
pick up on something you said a moment
ago. I remember you said there's a
terminal on every operating system. So
that leads me to two questions that I'm
hoping you can address. Number one, are
there specific terminal emulators that
you need to use to run rich or textual
applications? And then second of all,
does textual and rich applications run
on Windows, Mac OS, and Linux, or are
there restrictions? This is a
complicated question. It'll run just
about everywhere on any terminal, but
there are some caveats. On Mac OS, the
default terminal is limited to 256
colors and some of the block characters
don't work all that well. It's still
usable, but it's not pretty. So, in the
Mac, we do recommend downloading and
installing one of the other terminals
which are better in any other ways.
There is I term, wes term, kitty,
elacrity, ghosty which is a very recent
one which is very very good and the
textual experience on that is on all
those terminals is almost identical. The
same goes for other platforms as well.
So it'll work on Linux. Linux has great
support for for terminals. The default
terminal on any Linux distro will be
able to run textual apps very well. On
Windows, there's a different situation.
Microsoft released Windows Terminal a
few years ago and it's very feature
complete and it it runs textual apps
very well indeed. Prior to that, the
default Windows Terminal was pretty
poor. Microsoft hadn't done anything
with it in such a long time. The output
of textual apps was terrible. But if you
have Windows 10 or Windows 11, then text
apps will run beautifully on Windows
Terminal there. So, it's remarkably
universal. Textual Apps will run on all
the major platforms and virtually every
terminal out there. So, I noticed you
mentioned that it'll run on a wide
variety of terminal emulators and we can
pick the one that we prefer as long as
it's a relatively recent and modern one.
Are there restrictions when it comes to
the shell that you use? Like, can I use
bash or ZSH or fish or do I have to pick
a certain shell for my terminal? No, you
can use any shell you wish and the text
files will run as they always do. So,
one of the things I've noticed when I'm
building Python applications is that
sometimes it's a little bit challenging
to make sure it works across all
operating systems. Have you ever faced
any of those challenges when either you
were building textual or rich or
building an app using textual or rich?
Well, definitely building textual rich.
Yes. Even though the terminals work,
they're fairly compatible. They use the
same protocol, but when you do the kind
of work I do, you find the little subtle
differences and sometimes you do have to
compensate for those. The good thing is
that's all in the textual library
itself. If you're an app developer,
chances are you won't encounter any kind
of differences from one terminal to
another. Frankly, the situation is a
little bit better than browsers. I was a
web developer for for a number of years
and even though there are standards in
the web world, there are differences
with browsers. So, users will get a
slightly different experience and you
don't have any choice except to work
around those differences and they do
happen. I think the biggest challenge
with terminals is emoji support. Would
you believe it? I mean when terminals
came about no one could have possibly
conceived that people would be sending
little smiley faces to each other in the
terminal but nowadays everybody wants to
do that and the problem is that
terminals have varying support for uni
code and emoji. these emoji characters
that came out are sort of relatively
recent and the terminal will display
them, but there'll be inconsistencies in
how wide the characters are because some
characters can be twice as wide as your
average Latin alphabet character and
there's no way for textual to know how
wide those characters are going to be
and it will try to stick to the widths
that are set in the uni-ode database.
But sometimes the version of the
database that the terminal is using
isn't the same as a version of the
database that rich and text are using
and you can't know which is which. So
sometimes people will expect they will
write a unicode emoji and it'll break
the display in some annoying ways.
That's an example of something that we
can't work around unfortunately. That is
just an issue with terminals in general.
But if you restrict yourself to like a
subset of emojis in version 9, then
everything tends to work as you'd
expect. A moment ago, you mentioned
character encoding and you talked about
UTF8 when you were discussing emojis.
Can you briefly say what is a character
encoding and what is UTF8 and then how
do those terms connect to emojis? So
unicode is the standard way of
identifying characters. Characters is a
very broad term. The letter A is a
character and unic code the smiley face
is a character. Also all the Asian
characters the Korean, Chinese and
Japanese they're a character and Uni
code assigns essentially a number to
each of those codes but then you've got
to put it into actual data and there are
a number of different ways of squeezing
all this list of unique code points
which is numbers into actual bits and
byes. So that's a encoding. The most
popular encoding is UTF8 which is a
variable length. So some characters will
take up one bite. Some characters will
take up two, three or four bytes. For
the large part, you don't have to worry
about that because most terminals work
with UTF8 and those that don't rich and
textual will try to convert the output
into the encoding which the platform
supports. So yeah, you tend not to have
to worry about that with rich and
textual. is something that we have to
concern ourselves with. So I think the
good news that you're telling me is
you've done the hard work of building
rich and textuals so that when I'm
writing a program using those
frameworks, I don't have to know every
detail about how to get an emoji to
appear on the screen. No, exactly. The
developer, you don't have to concern
yourself with the frankly messy
implementation details. You just want to
write text, whatever that happens to be,
it gets quite complicated. One of the
major complicating factors is the fact
that a character can take up one cell or
two cell. A cell is the size that you
need to fit in a typical Latin alphabet
character. But Asian characters will
take up two cells. And if you're just
writing the text in a terminal, that
doesn't matter too much. But if you're
formatting it anyway, if you're putting
it inside a table, your code has to know
the exact width of the characters in
order to put in the rows and lines and
make it all neat and line up. So yeah,
that's something that the libraries
cater for because you don't want the
developer to have to think about that.
If they take in some input and it's in
Latin, you put your name in Latin and
Latin alphabet and that that works fine.
But then if another user from China puts
their their name in and they're using
Chinese characters which are twice the
width, it should just work. It should
just work. You shouldn't have to get
respond to issues about, hey, this
doesn't work in China, right? As a
developer, we just want to use libraries
and just be confident that things are
going to work wherever you happen to be
using the program. So what I'd like to
do now is build on what you just said
and talk further about how you actually
implemented rich and textual. And we'll
start with rich. When I've used Rich in
the past, I was impressed to see that
you can have like a table or you can
have text or a spinner or a progress
bar. Can you pick one of those and then
tell us a little bit about how you
actually built that feature? Sure. Yeah,
progress bars was a fun and interesting
one. So, there's multiple ways of
rendering a progress bar. I mean, um,
the older versions going back years
would use maybe like a hash or pound
symbol, then maybe like 20 of them and
would add another one as each time as
you move along, which is fine. That
works fine, but you can do a little
better graphically. There are a bunch of
characters in Uniode just for drawing
lines. So, you can combine these
together and you can get more
granularity. So, progress bars in rich,
you have two different characters per
cell. So it looks like there's more
steps on the progress bar. It makes it
look smoother. We added a bit of color
to that so the bar can be magenta and
the background gray so it makes it
easier to read. Um that was kind of a
visual thing. But what I find
interesting about the uh progress bars
as I did them and I made them look
pretty and then I got reports that it
was slowing down the code in which it
was running which kind of like sort of
defeats the purpose of having a a
progress bar. showing the progress bar
makes your application slower. And this
was happening because people were
running a bit of code that had multiple
steps and this the time between the
steps was was very small. So each step
might have taken a fraction of a second
even like you know hundth or thousandth
of a second and the progress code would
work with that. It's just it would
update that line of text 100 times a
second and that would slow it down. you.
So, you know, if you take like something
that's very fast, which rendering the
progress bar was, and you multiply it by
100 or thousand, it gets slower. Um, so
to solve that, we separated the updates
from the rendering. So now, if you do
like a,000 or 100,000 updates per
second, it'll only render 10 times per
second. So that means that the progress
bars no longer slow down the thing that
you're tracking the progress of. That
was a very interesting problem to solve.
So those are some interesting
experiences when it comes to actually
building a performant textual bar or
rich bar. And we're going to talk about
performance optimization later. One of
the things I noticed about the progress
bars that we were discussing is that you
can like decorate them with estimates
for how long a task is going to take or
how many of those tasks have been
completed. Am I remembering that
correctly? And then how did you actually
build in those additions that go along
with the progress bar? One of the great
things about Ridge is that you can
compose different renderables. You can
put a progress bar inside the table. So
if you want a progress bar with a few
other columns for the speed or the
estimated time to completion, you can do
that by putting the progress bar inside
a table and then adding other things to
the columns. And you can even display
multiple progress bars. So if your task
involves several things, you can track
them independently. So you can put
whatever you want in there. We have a
bunch of predefined columns for the
speed, estimated time of arrival, if
it's data that the speed will be shown
in bytes or kilobytes or megabytes per
second. And you can customize it. So if
you wanted to put something else inside
there, you could as well. Thanks for
that insight. Another thing that I
noticed is that Arri allows you to do
syntax highlighting of the code when you
display it in your terminal window. And
you can even then factor that into your
textual app as well and display nicely
formatted syntax highlighted code inside
of your app. So how does that work will?
It's really impressive. Yeah. So we have
I mentioned progress bars and tables and
etc. Those are all examples of
renderables. We also have a syntax
renderable and that takes code which
could be any kind of code be python C
even markdown SQL etc. and then it
applies syntax highlighting. We're using
the library pikements that parses the
code and then applies color to it. And
the renderable takes that information
and assembles it into one view. And it
can do a few other features like adding
line numbers, also indentation guides.
So the syntax renderable takes the code,
does all that work, spits out the
terminal, and it looks nice. It looks
like the code that you'd have in your
editor. And in textual, textual can
display these renderables as well cuz
it's built on textual is built on top of
rich. So it takes any rich renderable
such as the syntax display and then you
can put that inside a window and then
you can scroll it with the scroll bars
or up and down the keys and that
actually applies to any of the
renderables. If you build something in
rich and you want to display it inside a
window then it's just super easy. It's
just the same code essentially. You just
do widget update give it the renderable
and then it displays it there. Given
what you just said, there must be a way
when you're building a textual
application to define the layout like
the tree view goes to the left and the
syntax highlighted source code goes to
the right. Can you explain that feature
of textual in a little bit more detail?
Sure. So, one of the decisions I took
quite a while ago was to implement CSS,
which is a a browser technology inside
the terminal. seems like an odd decision
because CSS were designed for the web
and the terminal is quite a different
beast but it solves the same problems.
It separates the code from the
presentation. So there are a number of
like CSS rules which define layout. You
can create a horizontal list or a
vertical list. You can also create a
grid which is kind of like a table rows
columns and you can span rows and span
columns etc. And you can combine those
in almost an infinite number of ways. So
you can create a layout using just that
CSS. So it might seem like a complex
thing, but it boils down to half a dozen
lines of CSS and then you can tweak it
very easily. Part of the problem I had
with the previous generation of 2
frameworks, but it's very hard to
iterate. Yes, you could probably do
these layouts yourself and you'd have to
write a lot of code and if later you
decided, no, I don't like that thing on
the left of the screen. and I want to
move it to the right or I want to put it
at the bottom somewhere or I want to pop
it out of the screen and have it
floating over the top and that requires
a lot of code to change that. So the
advantage of CSS is that you can write
it very quickly and then you can change
it just as quickly. I read that textual
has like a reactive programming model
and that moreover it supports
asynchronous programming. Can you
explore those two concepts in slightly
greater detail so that we can get a full
featured understanding of what it's like
to program using textual? So I I come
from the web world and the great thing
about the web is that building user
interfaces has been iterated on very
rapidly for the last 10 20 years. People
have been trying new ways, new
interfaces, refining it and and creating
new technologies to create these user
interfaces. But none of that made it to
the terminal. The terminal is always
considered a bit archaic and people used
it for more simplistic outputs. So I I
took web technologies and essentially
ported what I think is the best of them
to the terminal. And one of those was
reactive variables. So in the web it
works a little bit differently than the
terminal, but essentially you create
attributes on your widget. A widget is
like a a visual component and then you
can assign to that attribute and magic
happens. Not real magic, it's a computer
magic, but you just change the data and
the UI will update accordingly and it
has a bunch of I call them superpowers.
For instance, if you assign to a
reactive attribute, you can have a
watcher which runs some code when it
changes. And that allows you to
basically create a very kind of elegant
interface where you're just changing the
data that describes your update and the
UI updates accordingly. And once you get
used to this way of working, you can
build quite powerful features with um
very little code. I like the way that
you said you're basically bringing
concepts from the web into the terminal
window. I had never thought about it
that way, but it really helped me to
understand some of the features and
programming models that are in textual.
Thanks for sharing that idea. Thank you.
Yes, like I said, I I love the web and
some of the features in web programming
are just so missing from the terminal.
Not everything. Not everything. I mean,
there's lots of stuff that we do in web
development which I do not like and I
don't wouldn't want to have anywhere
near the terminal. So, I like to think
I've cherrypicked the better
technologies and pull them into the
terminal world. I know you and your team
have really done a lot of engineering
work when it comes to like getting the
terminal applications to be fast and
there's several blog posts that you've
written about the strategies you've
adopted to make things fast for a 2e or
even for a CLI and we'll link the
listeners of our episode to some of
those so that they can read the articles
but there were several really thoughtful
phrases that were in the articles and
will if you don't mind I'm going to read
you a few of the phrases and then maybe
you could explain what you went through
and what you learned from the lesson
that I'm going to encapsulate in the
quick quotation. Does that sound cool?
Sure. Yeah. Let's let's do it. Yeah.
Okay. So, one of the things that you
wrote provocatively is that you should
overwrite instead of clearing. What does
that mean? You can consider the terminal
to be a matrix of characters. That's
essentially all it is. That composes all
the elements that run inside the
terminal. And if you change it, you can
build up a new frame. If you were to
clear the screen, which might be
obvious, and then write your new screen
on top of it, you get flicker because
the terminal was never really designed
in a sense it was, but it's not good at
displaying user interfaces. That's not
really its primary purpose, even though
it can. The way around that is instead
of clearing the screen, you just write
the new content on top of it. And you
don't need to change the bits of the
screen which have logically changed. And
textual does that by combining all the
updates that have happened within a 60th
of a frame and displays them all at
once. So that eliminates virtually all
flicker. But flicker can happen for a
number of reasons, but that kind of
reduces it to the bare minimum. It looks
just like a web app. Okay. So if you
don't clear, you avoid flicker. That
makes a lot of sense. Now, the next one
I'm going to talk about is perhaps a
little bit more in the land of Python
programming, but in one of your posts,
you said you should use immutable
objects. First of all, what is
immutability? And good grief, how does
that actually connect to performance?
Immutability is the opposite of
mutability. Mutability means the ability
to change, mutate your data. If an
object isn't mutable, it's immutable and
it can't change. And it might seem like
a restriction like you've got a data,
you got an object, you can't change it.
It might it feels like a restriction,
but that is massively beneficial. It
means that when you change it, you
create a new object rather than modify
an existing one. And when you do that,
caching works a lot better. So there's a
whole bunch of operations that happen in
textual where we take an object and we
apply a transformation to it and get new
data out of it. And that can be very
cachable, but that only works when
things are mutable. If the object can
change, then you can't cache it. So a
lot of our big speed wins came from
caching, and it came from making objects
immutable, which logically you might
think are are mutable. In the context of
Python programming, I'm familiar with
using the decorator that's called LRU
cache. Are you using something like that
or did you build your own caching
mechanism into textual enrich? We use
both. Yeah. Lu cache is terrific for
certain types of data. It was so easy.
You import it. You write at LRU cache.
You give it a max size. That's very
important for most data types. You don't
want it to increase infinitely cuz
eventually your memory will fail. But we
have other caching algorithms. There's a
cache. PI inside textual and that
includes an LRU cache that's implemented
as an object rather than a decorator and
we can use that in places where the
decorator doesn't quite fit and there's
also other caching algorithms and we
apply those quite liberally wherever
we've got a computation which is done
repeatedly but the input and output
doesn't change I forget what the term is
for that when you have the same input
you expect the same output those type of
operation ations can be cached and
whatever algorithm we use whether you
use the standard library or caching
classes it creates big wins as far as
runtime goes. Okay, so caching leads to
big wins. I noticed that both you and I
said LRU. Can you define what LRU is and
why that's important in the context of
caching? Oh, sure. LRU least recently
used. Basically, when you look something
up in a cache, it goes to the top of the
list and if you add something to the
cache, the least recently used item gets
discarded. So, you keep a a set that's
within max size and that contains the
elements which are most commonly used.
So, that tends to give you the bigger
speed win and that works if you're doing
operations where some items are
calculated more than others. You don't
want to keep an end result of a
calculation which isn't likely to be
used anytime soon but you do want to
keep the calculations which are likely
to be used more frequently. So that's
what the LRU in LRU cache does. So for
the LRU cache you mentioned there's a
maximum size. Do I specify that when I'm
creating my TUI using textual or did you
build that into textual? That's built
into textual. We've come up with just by
experimentation what the best size for
cache is. You want it to be large enough
to keep your most frequently used items.
Too large use up too much memory. Too
small and you don't get the benefits of
caching. So we've come up with a size of
the cache. And they tend to be quite
small power of two. I think many of them
are
like,24 items. And it depends on the
item how large you set the cache. If
your item is very small, if the output
is very small, just a few bytes, then
you can your caches could be larger. But
if your data is larger, you don't want
to keep around too many of them. So
yeah, it's something that we've thought
about and tweaked. Yeah, I can imagine
there's a trade-off between time
overhead and space overhead. And it
sounds like you have experimentally
evaluated what's the best trade-off for
textual. Yeah. Uh, a little bit
experimenting, a little bit kind of just
best judgment. You can watch what's
going on in these caches. The LU cache
decorator, it adds some attributes to
the function. So if you got a function
with an LU cache, you can do function
dot I think it's cache info and that'll
tell you how many hits and misses and
the size of the cache. So if you do that
and you see that you're getting lots of
hits, not many misses, then that
probably means you're about right with
the maximum size. If you find that
you're getting lots of misses, not many
hits, then you probably need to increase
the cache or even reconsider using a
cache at all. When it comes to
performance, I'm sure that one thing
that we often care about is the ability
to scroll in our terminal user interface
or if our CLI produces a lot of data, we
want to be able to scroll rapidly there
as well. And I know that many recent
terminal emulators use the GPU in order
to make smooth scrolling, but you've had
to think about how to do smooth
scrolling inside of the framework
itself. So, can you tell us a little bit
about some of your strategies for
ensuring that your two scroll in a
smooth fashion? Yeah, sure. So, yeah,
modern terminals use the GPU, which
means they're very good at spitting
characters onto the screen, but most of
scrolling happens inside your
application. So inside textual because
it has to render the next part of the
screen and then send that to the
terminal. So most of the work goes on
inside textual and there are a number of
ways to make it smoother. Initially just
means make it faster. If there's a lot
of computation going on to create the
screen and then you move a scroll bar,
you have to do that again. If that takes
half a second, you're going to get a
very unpleasant experience where you're
scrolling but the actual output is very
jittery. So we have to make it fast. we
have to like render as quickly as
possible. One of the ways we do that is
with caching that creates some very big
winds. For instance, one of the final
steps when we render a window is to turn
some internal data into escape
sequences. Uh the escape sequences are
what tells the terminal to change the
color background and style. We can cache
that for a given line. The output for
the escape sequences is not going to
change. So we cach that. So when you
scroll, you might reveal a line that
it's never seen before. That calculation
will be done there. It'll calculate the
sketch sequences and then it'll reuse
it. So when you're scrolling, it's not
doing much work at all. It's just
spitting out some text it has in memory.
And that is definitely a big part of
making scrolling smooth. But smooth has
different definitions to different
people. Some terminals, well actually
most terminals can report the mouse
coordinates in pixels. So you move the
mouse and it writes the coordinates in
pixels to standard input which textual
can then parse and you can use that
information to create even smoother
scrolling cuz the scroll bars can
actually render within a character.
They're block characters which render
scroll bars essentially and there's
eight of them. So you can render an
eighth of a cell, a character when
you're rendering the scroll bar. So the
scroll bar can look smooth and we use
that to make the scroll bars look
smooth. And we also make the window look
smooth by animating it accordingly. So
if you move the scroll bar one click,
the window might move two or three
lines. Now you could go from line zero
to line three or line four, but then it
would jump and that would be visually
obvious. But by animating it from 0 to
4, we go zero, then one, then two, then
three. It looks much smoother. It's a
bit of an illusion, but it just um to
the eye, it just looks like the text is
much smoother. So, there's lots of
things going on to create the illusion
of smooth scrolling. It can never be
100% smooth because the characters in
the window that you're moving, they can
only be in integer coordinates. They can
only go from one cell to the other. You
can't move a character up a pixel. it
has to move up a full character. So,
it's never going to be perfectly smooth
like a web browser. But with all these
optimizations, the caching, the pixel
movements, you can make it fairly smooth
to the eye to most people. Okay, that
makes a lot of sense. So, you were
talking about mouse coordinates. Another
thing I read in one of your articles is
that somehow it keeps inside of its
memory a spatial map. What's the spatial
map and how do you use that to support
smooth scrolling? That's not really a
smooth scrolling thing. Well, to some
extent. So, the spatial map when
everything's been laid out. Textual
records where all these things are. It
records the offset and the width and the
height of every single widget. And a
widget may contain other widgets. So, a
widget may contain a view with buttons
and check boxes, etc. All those have to
be laid out at the coordinates needed on
the screen. And the spatial map is a way
of very quickly figuring out what's
under the mouse. So if you click
something rather than go through all the
widgets, you can imagine it going
through a list of widgets and saying is
the mouse under this coordinate is the
mouse under this window. It
pre-calculates a lot of that. It's kind
it's kind of an index. So when you click
something, it does very little
computation to figure out exactly which
widget or widgets is underneath the
mouse. Thanks for that clarification. I
really appreciate it. We won't have time
to go into all of the steps that a
developer would take if they're going to
create a CLI or a TUI using frameworks
like Ridge or Textual. But one thing I
wanted to dwell on for a moment is the
testing aspect. So if I've built a TUI
using textual, what kinds of test cases
can I write to establish a confidence in
its correctness? So testing is obviously
very important to making robust
applications. And when we're building
textual, of course, we realized this
that if you want people to use it for
serious things, we have to make it
testable, which previously was was quite
tricky. So with the reactive system, you
can write tests quite easily because
you're writing data and then you can
check the results of the data. But often
the hardest thing to test are visual
aspects. You might make a change which
breaks the UI somewhere. Maybe a button
has been scrolled off the screen, etc.
So we have a snapshot testing system.
Basically you write a test which kind of
runs the application in a headless mode.
You can give it key presses and mouse
events etc. and it simulates it as if
you're using a real application and then
you can take a snapshot of the output
and the output is rendered into an SVG.
So we take the application what it looks
like inside a terminal but rather than
write it to terminal we write an SVG
file a scalable vector graphics file
which we could actually load in your
browser to visualize the application and
if you like that if you think that's
working correctly you save that snapshot
later on you decide to make some changes
maybe you move some things about you
change the style etc and it will tell
you what's changed in the output and
it'll put them side by side so you can
say is that correct or is that not
correct. It'll even overlay the new
screenshot on top of the old screenshot.
So if it's subtle, maybe a single button
has been moved or a bit of text has been
moved, you can see and visualize it. And
then you can make a decision. Does this
break it or is it just slightly
different? And if you accept it, then it
stores that screenshot the next time it
will do the whole thing all over again.
And it means that you can write quite
robust apps that are well tested. So
when you're doing the snapshot testing,
do you have the ability to maybe try
different font sizes? Can you try
different resolutions of your terminal
window? What works in that fashion? So
the font size is somewhat irrelevant
when it comes to testing cuz you make
the font bigger but the application will
scale uniformally. So the font size
doesn't come into the testing very much.
Sorry, what was the second part of your
The second thing that I was wondering
about is like the size of the terminal
window. Yes. So you can resize the
virtual application. So give it like a
terminal size of 100 or 200 and that'll
generate a larger screenshot. So if you
do have something and you want to test
it works on a small window versus a
large window, you can give it the size
of the application and you'll get a
larger SVG. So yeah, you can test for
various sizes of window. Okay, now I've
looked on GitHub and there are a whole
bunch of different systems that are
already using Textual. How do I actually
go about installing one of those
programs and using it in my own
terminal? It depends on the author of
the application, how they distributed
it, but generally it's through Pi,
Python package index. You basically
install the application and it adds a
command line. You run that command line
and it pops up the textual app.
Something newer in the Python world is
uh UV. It's kind of like a very grand
package manager. It has a really nice
feature in that you don't even have to
consciously install something. You do
uvx for instance we have the textual
demo. So you do uvx textual hyphen demo
that downloads it, installs it and runs
it in one command which is lovely. It
means you don't have to worry about
package managers and finding URLs and
downloading everything. All happens in
one. So I think that that is going to
come a very common way where people
distribute textual apps because it is
the lowest common denominator to getting
something installed. Just one command
line and it runs and when you want the
app again it's exactly the same command
line. Yeah, thanks for bringing up UV.
In fact, I use UVX to run most of my
textual apps now as well because it's
just so easy and additionally so
incredibly fast. Low effort, easy to
remember and yeah, it's it's very fast.
I'm surprised how fast it is. You would
kind of expect, you know, when
installing most applications, you're
sitting there looking at several
progress bars and you can go off and
have a cup of coffee. But because
textual apps are quite lean, it's only
just distributing a few dozen Python
files, maybe a few assets, it's also
fast. It downloads almost
instantaneously. I mean, they're much
smaller than your typical web page these
days. I mean, a 10 megaby web page is
fairly common, but for a textual app, I
don't know, it's going to be in the K.
It's going to be like a 100K or
something. Okay, so thanks for sharing
those details that are related to
testing and we've learned a little bit
more about how to actually install one
of these applications. I'm wondering if
you think about the current
implementations of your frameworks. Do
they have any limitations or do you have
any ideas for what the future might look
like and what you want to try to build
next? Yeah, text labs term lapse in
general, yeah, they do have
restrictions. They can only display
text. It kind of like blurs the
definition of what text is because
there's some characters to draw lines
and and corners and rounded edges etc.
But essentially it's just text.
Terminals don't do images terribly well.
Um there are a number of extensions to
the terminal protocol where you can work
with images in terms of pixels and not
characters. Textual doesn't support that
yet. It might do one day. It does
support very simple block characters. So
some of the unic code characters consist
of just squares and you can use them to
represent pixels, but they're quite low
resolution. So yeah, we don't have like
graphics generally as you would think of
in a web application. But that kind of
restriction is not really much of an
issue because the type of things that
you want to work with in the terminal
tend to be text based anyway. It tends
to be data. If you want rich graphics
and images and photographs, that's what
the web for. Terminal is for text and
and data and information and numbers.
So, when you've been talking throughout
our conversation today, we've been
saying the word text quite a bit, and it
made me think about the way that I often
interact with AI systems like Claude or
Chat GPT. That's also very textbased in
its fashion of interaction. Can you
comment briefly what do you see as some
of the interactions between CLIs and
TUIS and various AI based applications?
There's a few applications which
basically talk to chat bots. The textual
app has a text input. You write in your
prompt and then it contacts the API and
then response is displayed in the
window. So it's it's a great way of
doing developer kind of things with AI
in the terminal where you want to work
with the the data. One source
application is Eliia which I'm sure
you'll find a link to and that is a chat
GPT client that built with textual. It
looks great and it looks just as good as
web applications. And also to flip it
around a bit AI is getting better
writing applications in textual. Claude,
I think, is the best one I've used so
far, but it changes weekly. If you go to
Claude and ask it to build a textual
app, it will generally get there. You
might take a couple of prompts, maybe it
will hallucinate a method name or
something, and you just tell it, "No,
that doesn't exist, and it fixes it."
And you can get quite far with very
little programming, just basically
typing prompts to build applications,
which you can then run inside the
terminal. And you can continue to edit
with AI or you could just open up your
editor and then tweak it in code. Thanks
for that response. We've talked a lot
about CLIs and two and you've given us
some insights in terms of how they work
with either rich or textual or both
combined together. Are there additional
topics that we didn't discuss that you
think we should chat about now? I'm sure
there's plenty we could discuss. Kind of
drawing a blank here. Craig, did you
have any ideas, sir? No, I think what
we've talked about so far has been
really good. The only thing that I
wanted to dive into further is some
advice that you might give to a
programmer who wants to get started with
building a CLI or a TUI. They may or may
not know Python, but if you could just
broadly comment, what steps do you think
someone should take if they want to
create their own CLI or 2E or maybe even
build their own 2E framework? So there's
lots of options. People are different
types of learners. Personally, I I read
docs. I go into the docs and I I devour
them and then I start coding. If that's
what you like, the docs are available
for our projects and other projects. So
I just go read the docs. If that's not
your thing, you might want examples. And
there's plenty of examples on on the
web. We have lots of examples of our
projects. But if you go to GitHub and
find an application which you think is
quite close to what you would want, have
a look at how the other developer did
it. If it's a good project, it'll be
commented and you should be able to
follow it quite easily. There is a
learning curve of course, but it's not
uncsurmountable even from scratch.
There's lots of friendly people who are
willing to help. I mean, our Discord
server is full of people coming on who
have not much experience. They ask a few
questions, get them started. We'll send
them in the right direction. Yeah, they
can do it that way. You build on your
knowledge layer by layer by
experimenting, changing, tweaking, and
that kind of mindset doesn't actually
change whether you're first year in
programming or you've been doing it for
30 years. It's it's a continual process
of like experimentation, trying
something, refining it, and repeat.
Thank you for that call to action and
the invitation to join the community.
We'll make sure to link the listeners of
our show to some of the resources that
are available on like the textual
website or the rich website and we'll
include some links in the show notes to
some sample applications as well. Yeah,
sounds good. Yeah, lots of information
there. So, will thank you for taking all
of this time to chat with us today about
how to build tuies and CLIs using
frameworks like rich and textual. For
me, it's been a informative and fun
conversation. Thank you for joining
today. Thank you, Greg. It's been a
pleasure. Thank you. Thanks to all of
our listeners of Software Engineering
Radio. See you next time.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
ITLE E Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
to provide feedback.